Welcome to our program!
皆さん ようこそ！
Here are just a few of the things
we can look forward to:
今回 考慮するのは次の事柄です
Can the lure of fame
draw us away from Jehovah?
名声を求めるならエホバから
離れてしまうでしょうか？
How does this brother
feel about the decisions
自分の下した決定について
この兄弟はどう思ったでしょうか？
he made as a young person?
What does his story teach us
賜物や才能をどのように
用いるべきかについてー
about how to use our
God-given abilities and talents?
何を学べるでしょうか？
Throughout the organization, young brothers
and sisters are reaching out
若者たちはエホバの組織の中でさらに
多くの事を行なう資格をとらえています
to do more in Jehovah’s service.
Their spirituality and youthful energy
彼らの霊性や若い力は
王国の業の前進に貢献しています
are helping to advance
the Kingdom work.
But how is showing respect
for experienced brothers
しかし 神権的な割り当てにおいて—
経験ある兄弟たちに敬意を示すことは
どのように重要でしょうか？
an important part
of any theocratic assignment?
We’ll also hear
from young brothers and sisters
世界中の若い兄弟姉妹たちからも
話を聞きましょう
from around the world.
Why is their relationship with Jehovah
so important to them?
エホバとの関係は彼らにとって
なぜ重要でしょうか？
What do they do to build
and maintain their spirituality?
霊性を高めて維持するために
何を行なっているでしょうか？
クリスチャンの若者たちが
世界中の仲間の兄弟たちに—
And we’ll consider
even more ways Christian youths
are setting a beautiful example
for our worldwide brotherhood.
素晴らしい模範を示せる
ほかの方法についても考慮します
This is JW Broadcasting
for December 2016!
それでは 2016年12月の
JW Broadcastingです!
During the past five years,
過去5年の間に
130万以上の忠実な人々が—
over 1.3 million faithful ones
エホバへの献身の象徴として
水のバプテスマを受けました
have symbolized their dedication
to Jehovah by water baptism.
That’s an average
of over 700 each day.
平均すると 毎日700人ほどです
And among those
courageously taking their stand
真の崇拝の側に
立場を定めた人の中には—
for true worship
are thousands of children,
幾千人もの子どもたちや
若い人々が含まれています
teenagers, and young adults.
Young brothers and sisters,
若い兄弟姉妹—
we know it is not always easy
エホバにお仕えし
献身にふさわしく生きることが—
to serve Jehovah
and live up to your dedication.
容易でないときもあるでしょう
Like older ones,
年長の人々と同様—
you need to be encouraged
and strengthened spiritually.
皆さんも 霊的に励ましを受け
強められる必要があります
With that in mind,
our theme this month is
それで今月は—
若いクリスチャンであった
テモテの生き方に注目し—
“Young Ones, ‘Become an Example
to the Faithful Ones.’”
“若い皆さん
「忠実な者たちの手本」となりなさい”—
It is based on the inspiring true-life story
という主題で話をしたいと思います
of a young Christian named Timothy.
Before we discuss Timothy’s example,
皆さんは 現代に多くの若者が
エホバの側に立場を定めることが—
did you know that the Bible
specifically foretold
聖書によって予告されていたことを
ご存じでしょうか？
that many young people would take
sides with Jehovah in our time?
Let’s look at this at Psalm 110:3.
詩編 110編3節を見てみましょう
And as we read it together,
聖句を読む際に—
皆さんが
この預言の成就に—
note how young ones are having a share
in fulfilling this prophecy.
どのように関わっているかを
考えてみましょう
Notice the first part of verse 3,
3節の前半で
ダビデはこう歌っています
David sang:
“Your people will offer themselves willingly
“あなたの軍勢の日に あなたの民は
進んで自らをささげます”
on the day of your military force.”
According to this prophecy, Jesus,
the Messianic King,
この預言の通り
メシアなる王イエスは—
進んで仕える人々の軍勢を
有することになっていました
would have a large army
of willing supporters.
Since 1914, millions have carefully
investigated the facts
1914年以来 多くの人々が
事実を注意深く調べ—
and chosen to side
with Jehovah God and Jesus Christ.
エホバとイエスの側に
立場を定めてきました
But where do young ones
come into this picture?
では 若い人はどうでしょうか？
The rest of the verse continues:
聖句はこう続けています
“In splendid holiness,
from the womb of the dawn,
“神聖さの光輝のうちに
夜明けの胎から—”
“you have your company of young men
“あなたは露玉のような
若者の隊を得ておられます”
just like dewdrops.”
Here, the prophecy refers to a “company,”
or group, of young ones.
この預言は
若者たちの一群に言及しています
They also would study the evidence
and support God’s Kingdom.
若い人々も 証拠を調べ
神の王国を支持するのです
How many young people
did Jehovah foresee
どれほどの若者がそうすることを
神は予見しておられたでしょうか？
supporting true worship?
We get an idea by the comparison
made to dewdrops.
露玉という表現に注目すると
その点を理解できます
Have you have ever gone outside
early in the morning
皆さんは 朝早く外に出て
草花に付いた水分が—
and noticed a light, sparkling coating
of water on the ground?
光り輝いているのを
見たことがありますか？
That may have been dew.
それが露です
Jehovah designed our atmosphere so that,
under certain conditions,
エホバは大気を造られたとき—
夜間に気温が下がると
大気中の水分が冷えて—
when the temperature
cools during the night,
地面に到達するようにされました
a blanket of moisture
forms on the ground.
That coating is made up
of a multitude of little drops.
こうして生じる水分は
沢山の小さな滴となります
若い皆さん—
Young ones,
what does dew have to do with you?
露は 皆さんと
どんな関係がありますか？
In the Bible, dew is connected
with blessing and abundance.
露は聖書中で 祝福や豊かさを
表わして用いられます
Dewdrops are also refreshing,
同様に露玉も さわやかさをもたらし
命を支えます
life-sustaining, and numerous.
Now, remember in Psalm 110:3,
さて 詩編 110編3節で—
Jehovah was looking ahead to our time.
エホバはわたしたちの時代に
目を向けておられました
And what did he see?
何をご覧になったでしょうか？
The September 15, 2002,
Watchtower on page 8
「ものみの塔」誌 2002年9月15日号
8ページにはこうあります
explained it this way:
“Just like refreshing dewdrops,
“まさにさわやかな露玉のように—”
“many young men and women
cheerfully serve God
“多くの若い男女が喜んで神に仕え
仲間の崇拝者たちを助けているのです”
and assist their fellow worshipers.”
Today, there are so many mature,
今日のクリスチャン会衆には—
円熟し 快活で 幸福に満ちた
若者たちが大勢います
bright, happy young ones
in the Christian congregation
彼らは 朝日に照らされ輝く
露玉のようにきらめいています
that they are like countless dewdrops
that sparkle in the morning sun.
You faithful children, teenagers,
エホバに献身した あるいは—
その目標に向かって進歩している
忠実な子どもたちや若い人々は—
and young adults who have dedicated
your life to Jehovah
or who are working toward that goal
若者たちに関して
エホバが抱かれた確信が—
are living proof that Jehovah’s confidence
決して間違っていなかったことの
生きた証拠と言えます
in young people was never misplaced.
He cherishes you very much and so do we.
皆さんは エホバとわたしたちにとって
大切な存在です
Of course, knowing
that Jehovah has confidence in us
このように—
エホバがわたしたちに確信を
置いてくださっているということは—
can be very encouraging.
大きな励みとなりますが—
But what if doubts or negative thoughts
時には 疑いや消極的な気持ちで
気落ちすることもあるでしょう
tend to bring us down?
On occasion,
a young Witness might wonder,
時折—
“エホバ以外にわたしを
気にかけてくれる人がいるだろうか？”
‘Does anyone other
than Jehovah notice me?
“自分の手本など 他の人に影響を
与えるだろうか？”—
Does my example really matter to others?’
と考えるかもしれません
To address these questions,
そうした疑問に答えるため
テモテの模範について考慮しましょう
let’s now consider Timothy’s example.
Open your Bible, please,
主題聖句である
テモテ第一 4章12節を開きましょう
to our theme text at 1 Timothy 4:12.
When you find it,
you might want to bookmark the verse
開けたら そこをすぐ
読めるようにしておいて—
because we want to first
understand the setting.
まず背景を考えてみましょう
How old was Timothy at this time?
このとき テモテは何歳でしたか？
Often, when thinking of Timothy,
テモテというと 十代か二十代前半の
若者をイメージするかもしれません
I picture a teenager or a young man
in his early twenties.
And when he
first started traveling with Paul,
確かに パウロと
旅行を始めたのはその頃でした
he was about that age.
しかし パウロが彼に
手紙を書いたのは—
But several years passed
before Paul wrote letters to Timothy.
それから何年も経ってからでした
So by the time
First Timothy was written,
それで テモテへの
最初の手紙が書かれたとき—
Timothy was likely in his early thirties.
彼はすでに
30代前半だったでしょう
Now, what do you think?
どう思われますか？
Was Timothy young or old?
テモテは 若かったと言えますか？
若い皆さんは
“30代なんてもう若くない”—
Some of you younger ones
may be thinking to yourselves,
‘If he was over 30,
then he was old!’
“結構な歳だ”
と言うかもしれません
But remember,
a much older man like Paul
でも パウロのような
年長者から見れば—
テモテは依然として
とても若い兄弟でした
would say that Timothy was quite young.
In fact, notice the expression
he uses when writing to Timothy.
テモテへの手紙で
用いられている表現に注目しましょう
First Timothy 4:12, Paul says:
テモテ第一 4章12節にこうあります
“Never let anyone
look down on your youth.
“あなたの若さをだれにも
見下げられることのないようにしなさい”
“Instead, become an example
to the faithful ones
“かえって 語ることにも 行状にも
愛にも 信仰にも 貞潔さにも—”
“in speaking, in conduct, in love,
“忠実な者たちの手本となりなさい”
in faith, in chasteness.”
Paul called Timothy a youth
and urged him to be a good example.
パウロは テモテの若さに言及し
良い手本となるよう勧めました
While Timothy may have been
in his early thirties at this time,
この時すでに 30代に達していたと
思われるテモテは—
remember that he
was taught about Jehovah
幼い時から
エホバの教えを受けていました
from the time he was a baby,
そして 若者に成長してからも
真理のうちを歩んでいました
and he did well in the truth
as a young person.
In fact, when he was still a teenager
or in his early twenties,
さらに 10代から20代後半には—
パウロと共に 宣教者として
奉仕するよう推薦されました
the elders recommended him
to serve as a missionary with Paul.
So, in effect,
Paul here is urging Timothy
ですから パウロはここで
引き続き良い手本であるよう—
to continue to be
a good example for others.
テモテに勧めていたのです
テモテについて 他にも
どんなことを知っていますか?
What else do we know about Timothy?
He was not proud, or haughty.
彼は 誇り高ぶった人では
ありませんでした
He likely did not view himself
as some amazing example.
自分のことを 素晴らしい手本だ
などとは思っていなかったでしょう
I’m sure he never dreamed
that one day Christians all over the world
やがて世界中のクリスチャンが—
自分の信仰に倣うため
その歩みを調べることになるとは—
would study his life in detail
so as to imitate his faith.
夢にも思っていなかったはずです
Timothy was modest
—and this despite his privileges.
多くの責任を担っていましたが
テモテは慎みを示しました
Paul’s words may indicate
that Timothy was somewhat shy.
パウロの言葉からすると
テモテは内気でもあったようです
Like many of us,
わたしたちと同じように—
he may have battled with feelings
of self-doubt on occasion.
自信を失いそうに
なることもあったでしょう
Based on this information,
let’s do something interesting now.
そうしたことを念頭に置きながら
こう考えてみましょう
Let’s use our imagination
to visualize Timothy,
まず 想像力を働かせて
テモテを思い浮かべましょう
an elder in his early thirties,
30代前半の長老だった彼が
会衆で話をするためにやってきます
coming to give a Scriptural talk
in the congregation.
Got the picture?
見えてきましたか？
In your mind,
please look at Timothy
心の中でテモテと聴衆を
思い描いてください
and then look at the audience.
Who do we see?
聴衆の中には—
Many in attendance are old enough
彼の親か 祖父母ほどの年長者も
大勢いたことでしょう
to be Timothy’s parents
or grandparents.
How do you think Timothy felt?
どう感じたでしょうか?
Super confident?
自信満々で 威張った様子で
集会所に入ってきて—
Are you visualizing him proudly walking
into the meeting place, saying:
“ルステラにいる友人たちにも—”
“I sure wish my friends back
in Lystra could see me now.
“わたしの話を聞くために集まった
この群衆を見て欲しい”—
Look at the crowds
that come to hear me speak!”
などと言ったでしょうか？
No, that’s not the Timothy we know.
わたしたちの知っているテモテなら
そうではなかったはずです
It’s much more likely that Timothy,
like most of us,
むしろ わたしたちと同じように—
何度も 何度も 話の練習を
繰り返したことでしょう
rehearsed his presentation
over and over again.
He probably prayed constantly,
どんなに祈りを捧げても—
緊張を完全に拭うことは
できなかったでしょう
and he probably still got nervous,
like all of us.
And remember,
Timothy did not have the benefit
しかもテモテには 今日のような
神権的な学校はありませんでした
of theocratic schools like we do today.
In summary,
要約すると
テモテはどんな人でしたか？
what can we say about Timothy?
Like so many of you,
皆さんの多くと同じように
彼は 信仰と従順の手本でした
he was an example
of faith and obedience.
He was exceptional
in displaying Christian qualities,
そして 慎みや謙遜さといった
特質を示す点で際立っていました
such as modesty and humility.
But Timothy was a person
with normal human feelings,
一方で テモテは 通常の人間の
感覚を有していました
like all of us.
Though he had a rich,
happy life in Jehovah’s service,
エホバに幸福に仕えていたとはいえ—
サタンの世からもたらされる
多くの試練も経験したでしょう
life in the old world
brought real tests and challenges.
Timothy also dealt
with frequent cases of sickness,
度重なる病気を経験し
投獄されたこともありました
and he was imprisoned for a time.
Some of you in various countries
同じような 苦い経験をしてきた
方々もおられるでしょう
can relate to those bitter experiences.
But Timothy endured.
それでも テモテは忍耐しました
Was he some “super Christian”
with superpowers?
超越した力を持つ “スーパークリスチャン”
だったのでしょうか？
No, but he did
prove to be a super example!
そうではありません
でも その手本は
確かに超越していました
How does all of this
help you Christian youths
こうしたことは—
エホバへの献身という段階を経た若者にとって
どのように助けとなるでしょうか？
who have taken the commendable step
to dedicate your lives to Jehovah?
We just read how Paul told Timothy
to let no one look down on his youth.
パウロはテモテに 若さを
見下げられないようにと勧めました
A few of you may be thinking,
もしかするとある人は—
“わたしを見下げないように
うちの親や長老たちに言ってほしい”
‘I wish someone would tell my parents
‘or my elders not to look down on me.
“わたしを子ども扱いするから”
と考えるかもしれません
They still treat me like a little kid.’
If that’s the case,
we feel for you.
その気持ちはよくわかります
No progressive young one
wants to be treated as if he were a child.
進歩したいと願っている若者なら
子ども扱いは 嫌でしょう
でも もう一度
テモテ第一 4章12節を見てみましょう
But let’s look again at 1 Timothy 4:12.
Is the apostle Paul speaking
to the congregation,
パウロは 会衆や 親や 長老たちに
対して語っていたのでしょうか？
to parents, or to the elders?
“Never let anyone look down
“あなたの若さをだれにも
見下げられることのないようにしなさい”
“on your youth.
“Instead, become an example
to the faithful ones in speaking,
“かえって 語ることにも 行状にも
愛にも 信仰にも 貞潔さにも—”
in conduct, in love,
in faith, in chasteness.”
“忠実な者たちの手本となりなさい”
It’s clear, isn’t it?
答えは明らかですね
Paul said your youth.
パウロは若い人に語りました
He was speaking only to Timothy.
テモテに対して述べたのです
Young ones, by extension,
what is Jehovah saying to each of you?
若い皆さん エホバは皆さんにも
こうおっしゃっています
It’s this: To gain and maintain
the respect of faithful ones,
忠実な人たちから敬意を勝ち得て
それを保ちなさい
you have to work
at proving yourself as a Christian.
クリスチャンであることを
自分の生き方で示しなさい
The key is not wanting or hoping
that others will respect you.
他の人が敬意を示してくれるのを
ただ待っているのではなく—
Rather, it’s earning such respect
by setting a good example
生活のあらゆる面で
良い手本となることで—
敬意を得るよう努めなさい
in all areas of life.
If you do that,
そうすれば 誰もあなたを
見下げることはないでしょう
then no one will have any legitimate reason
to look down on your youth.
Doesn’t it make sense
that we gain respect by earning it?
努力して敬意を勝ち得るというのは
道理にかなっていると思いませんか？
皆さんは 学校や 地域社会で—
We are confident
that you young ones are trying hard
クリスチャンの原則に沿って生きるよう
賢明に努力していることでしょう
to live by Christian principles at school
and in the neighborhood.
But in verse 12, did you notice
who Timothy was to be an example to?
しかし12節で テモテは誰の手本と
なるようにと言われていますか？
To “the faithful ones.”
“忠実な者たち”です
Are you an example to Christians,
both younger and older,
皆さんは 会衆や巡回区で—
同年代やあるいは 年長のクリスチャンの
手本となっていますか？
in your congregation
and in your circuit?
If you work on Kingdom Hall
construction projects or at Bethel,
王国会館建設プロジェクトや
ベテルで奉仕しているなら—
are you an example
to your fellow workers?
他の奉仕者の手本と
なっているでしょうか？
Well, what are some specific ways
you can become an example
具体的にどのような面で—
”忠実な者たち”の手本と
なることができるのでしょうか？
to all of these “faithful ones”?
In our theme text,
Timothy was first directed
聖句によれば テモテは—
まず 語ることにおいて
手本となるよう勧められました
to become an example in speaking.
On this topic,
I’ll never forget an illustration
この点について 2012年1月号の
「目ざめよ！」誌に掲載された—
used in the “Young People Ask” article
from the January 2012 Awake!
「若い人は尋ねる」の記事の
例えを思い出します
It quoted a young man,
James, who said:
ジェームズという若者は
こう述べました
“Once you squeeze toothpaste out,
you can’t put it back in the tube.
“歯磨き粉を一度チューブから
出すと もう戻せません”
“The same is true with our words.
“口から出す言葉も同じです”
Once we say something hurtful,
we can’t take it back.”
“傷つけるようなことを言ったら
もう戻せません”
この言葉は 聖書とも調和しています
God’s Word agrees with James.
Note what it says at Ephesians 4:29.
エフェソス 4章29節を見てみましょう
It tells us:
こうあります
“腐ったことばを あなた方の口から
出さないようにしなさい”
“Let a rotten word
not come out of your mouth,
“むしろ 必要に応じ
どんなことにせよ—”
“but only what is good
for building up as the need may be,
“築き上げるのに
良いことばを出して—”
to impart what is beneficial
to the hearers.”
“聞く人たちに
恵みとなるようにしなさい”
For some years now,
those getting baptized
近年 バプテスマを受けた人には—
have been encouraged
to complete a study of the book,
「神の愛」の本を研究し終えるよう
励まされてきました
“Keep Yourselves in God’s Love.”
Chapter 12 is entitled
“Speak What ‘Is Good for Building Up.’”
12章の主題は—
”「築き上げるのに良い」事柄を語る”
というもので—
On page 140,
there is a box with five questions
140ページの囲みには—
自分の言葉を吟味するための
5つの質問が載せられています
that can help us evaluate our speech.
For example:
例えば—
前回だれかに具体的な褒め言葉を
かけたのはいつのことだっただろうか？
“When was the last time I offered
someone specific commendation?
“Do I express my respect for others
by saying please and thank you?
”どうぞ”あるいは
”ありがとう”と言って—
他の人への敬意を
表わしているだろうか？
“In conversation,
do I speak mainly about myself,
会話の際に
自分のことばかり話すだろうか—
それとも 他の人の考えや気持ちにも
関心を払っているだろうか? などです
or am I also interested
in the thoughts and feelings of others?”
Young ones,
over the next few days,
若い皆さん これから数日をかけて
この囲みを振り返り—
why not review that box on page 140,
look up the scriptures,
聖句を開いて エホバの述べていること
を考慮するのはどうですか？
and think about what Jehovah is saying?
Then apply what you learn to your speech.
そして それを自分の話し方に
当てはめましょう
Doing this will draw you closer to Jehovah
そうすれば
一層エホバに引き寄せられ—
and help you to become
an even better example
忠実な人々のより良い手本と
なることができるでしょう
to the faithful ones.
The second area
mentioned in our theme text
聖句の中で二番目に言及されていたのは
行状における手本です
is becoming an example in conduct.
Of course,
upbuilding speech would be empty
言うまでもなく
疑わしい振る舞いをしているなら—
or hypocritical
if our conduct was questionable.
築き上げる言葉を用いても
虚しく 偽善的に聞こえるでしょう
Think again about Timothy.
テモテはどうでしたか？
It wasn’t enough for him to give comments
and talks at the meetings
期待されていたのは 集会の出席や
注解や宣教だけではありませんでした
or preach from door to door.
Later in the same letter,
Paul reminded Timothy
パウロは 同じ手紙の中で
年長の男子や婦人には父や母のように—
that he needed to treat older men
and women as fathers and mothers;
若い男子や婦人には
兄弟や姉妹のように接するよう—
younger men and women
were to be treated as brothers and sisters.
テモテに勧めました
Second Peter 3:11
ペテロ第二 3章11節も—
provides a similar urgent reminder
about our conduct.
わたしたちの振る舞いに関して
同様の諭しを与えています
Let’s read that together.
読んでみましょう
ペテロ第二 3章11節です
Again, that’s 2 Peter 3:11.
There it tells us:
そこには—
“Since all these things
are to be dissolved in this way,
“これらのものは こうして
ことごとく溶解するのですから—”
“consider what sort of people
you ought to be
“あなた方は聖なる行状と
敬虔な専心のうちに”とあります
in holy acts of conduct.”
Let’s think about that.
考えてみましょう
For a person’s conduct to be holy
from Jehovah’s perspective,
ある人の行状が エホバの見地から
聖なるものとみなされるには—
he or she must be morally clean.
道徳的な清さが求められます
身体的清さは
外面と関係しますが—
While physical cleanness
is on the outside,
道徳的な清さには
内面 つまり思いや欲求が関係しています
moral cleanness is on the inside
—in our thoughts and desires.
Is being morally clean really important?
なぜ 道徳的清さが
重要なのでしょうか？
Think about it this way.
こう考えてみましょう
When eating a meal,
would you be content to eat from a bowl
皆さんは 食事をするとき—
外側しか洗っていない器で
食べたいと思いますか？
that had been washed
only on the outside?
Of course not!
そんなことはないでしょう
We want to eat from clean dishes
外側も内側も きれいな器で
食べたいと思うはずです
—dishes that are
thoroughly clean inside and out.
So when we wash dishes,
we wash the outside and the inside.
ですから 食器を洗う時には
外側も内側も きれいにします
Similarly,
Jehovah expects his servants
同じようにエホバは—
ご自分の僕が あらゆる面で
清いことを願っておられます
to be clean through and through.
And because Jehovah
—the perfect reader of hearts—
心をすべてご覧になるエホバは—
間もなく 汚れた事物の体制を
滅ぼし尽くされます
will soon dissolve, yes,
eliminate this dirty system of things,
ですから 清さを保つことは
急務なのです
it’s urgent that we do so.
This means
that we have to work very hard
それで 汚れたものを
何も心に取り入れないよう—
so that nothing unclean
enters our mind.
懸命に努力すべきです
That means firmly rejecting
このことには 性や暴力や
心霊術が関係している娯楽を—
so-called fun
and exciting entertainment,
断固として退けることが
含まれています
which features sex,
violence, or spiritism.
At 1 Corinthians 14:20,
the Bible tells us
聖書は コリント第一 14章20節で—
“悪に関しては みどりごで
ありなさい”と勧めています
that we should become
like “young children as to badness.”
No matter our age,
年齢にかかわらず
わたしたちはこの世のいかなる悪も—
we don’t need and we don’t want
経験したいと思いませんし
その必要もありません
any experience
with the wickedness of this world.
むしろ わたしたちは器の内側を
つまり 思いと心をいつでも清く保ちます
Rather,
we keep the inside of the dish,
our mind and heart,
clean at all times.
And when we do so,
our exemplary conduct
そうするなら わたしたちの模範的な
振る舞いは エホバを喜ばせ—
pleases Jehovah and it strengthens
our faithful brothers and sisters.
忠実な兄弟姉妹を
強めるものとなるのです
Really, it’s the only way
to respect ourselves
そして それは他の人から
敬意を得る方法でもあるのです
and to gain the respect of others.
Our theme text at 1 Timothy 4:12
主題聖句である
テモテ第一 4章12節は—
goes on to mention other areas
手本となれるよう成長できる
他の分野にも言及しています
where we can make steady progress
in becoming an example,
それは愛 信仰 貞潔さなどです
such as in love, in faith,
and in chasteness.
During your personal study,
個人研究 つまり最高の友である
エホバとの個人的な時間に—
that is, your personal time
with your best Friend, Jehovah,
これらの要素についても
詳しく調べてみるのはいかがですか？
why not examine these areas
in more detail?
The treasures you gain
from such a study project
そうした研究プロジェクトから
得られる宝は—
can last a lifetime
—an everlasting lifetime.
永遠に続く生涯にわたって
価値あるものとなるでしょう
So, what have we learned?
振り返ってみましょう
In fulfillment of Bible prophecy,
聖書預言の成就として
世界中の大勢の若者たちが—
a large company of young people
from around the world
エホバとイエスの側に
立場を定めています
are taking a stand
with Jehovah and Jesus.
That includes all of you.
そこには皆さんも含まれています
Like dewdrops,
you’re not only abundant in number
皆さんは 露玉のように—
数の点で多いだけでなく
会衆の中で光り輝いています
but you sparkle in our congregations.
Your presence is very refreshing.
皆さんの存在は
とてもさわやかです
So please,
don’t look down on your youth.
それで ご自分の若さを過小評価せず
むしろ 喜びあるものとしてください
Rather, rejoice in your youth!
Yes, “become an example
to the faithful ones”!
そして “忠実な者たちの手本”と
なりましょう！
In the following dramatization,
次のドラマの中で 若い兄弟は
今 考慮した事柄を行なっています
a young brother is doing
just what we’ve discussed.
He’s becoming an example
to faithful ones
忠実な者たちの模範となって
割り当てを一生懸命果たしています
and working hard
at the assignments he is given.
But there’s something he lacks
でも 何か足りません
—a quality that would make him
それは エホバと会衆にとって
もっと有用な者となるための特質です
even more valuable to Jehovah
and to the congregation.
集会前の準備は ぼくの仕事です
Before the meeting starts,
I need to get things ready.
I’m Ben.
ベンです
And as a ministerial servant,
奉仕の僕です
I can do a lot
to help the congregation.
会衆のために
たくさんのことをしています
And that night
I was given another assignment.
集会後 リチャーズ兄弟から
新しい仕事を頼まれました
Brother Richards asked if I could help him
update the territory maps
区域地図を新しくすることと—
公の奉仕の予定を組むことです
and organize our schedules
for public witnessing.
I think the brothers know
I can modernize all of this.
ぼくなら 最新のやり方でできると
思ってくれたんだと思います
Brother Richards said to talk
to Brother Bello, first.
まず ベロー兄弟と話し合うようにと
言われました
He was the service overseer for years.
長年 奉仕監督として
奉仕してくださっている兄弟です
Great idea!
これはこれでいいけど…
But I can already imagine
the possibilities.
もう自分なりのいい考えが
浮かんでいました
By that weekend,
I had almost finished.
週末には 区域地図はほぼ一新
I couldn’t believe the outdated ways
our records were kept.
正直 今までのやり方は
古くさくてびっくりでした
This is going to be way better
for the congregation.
会衆にとっては
こっちのほうがずっといい—
And who knows
what else could be improved?
これ以上のものはない
そう思いました
I thought I had everything ready
to show Brother Richards.
さっそく 仕上がり具合を
リチャーズ兄弟に見てもらいました
He liked the new ideas,
but then he asked me,
ほめてもらえたけど—
でも こう尋ねられました
“What did Brother Bello think?”
“ベロー兄弟のお考えは
どうなのかな？”
Oh, Brother Bello!
I forgot.
しまった ベロー兄弟！
忘れてた 話をするんだった...
I should have asked him,
but at this point,
did it really matter?
でも これでいいんじゃないかなぁ
Brother Richards suggested
we read about Elisha.
兄弟と一緒に
エリシャの話を読むことになりました
エリヤの務めが終わろうとしていた時—
When the older Elijah’s work was ending,
エリシャは教師であるエリヤから
離れようとはしませんでした
Elisha stuck close to his teacher.
Urged to stay behind,
Elisha repeatedly said:
ここに残るようにと言われても—
繰り返しこう答えました
“As surely as Jehovah is living
and as you are living,
“エホバは生きておられ
あなたの魂も生きています”
I will not leave you.”
“私はあなたを離れません”
Until the moment Elijah left,
エリヤが取られるその時まで—
Elisha wanted to learn from him.
エリヤから学ぼうとしたんです
Like a son asking his father,
父親にお願いする子どものように—
he wanted a double portion
of Elijah’s spirit
これからの奉仕のために—
エリヤの霊の二つの分を
与えてほしいと頼みました
to continue the work he started.
And Elisha’s first miracle
そして エリシャが
最初に行なった奇跡は—
was the same as Elijah’s last:
エリヤの最後の奇跡と同じもの—
エリヤの職服でヨルダン川を分ける
というものでした
dividing the Jordan
with Elijah’s official garment.
Everything Elisha did
revealed his respect
エリシャの行なうことすべてに—
経験あるエリヤに対する
敬意が表われていました
for the experienced man Elijah.
I wasn’t finished
with my new assignment after all.
まだ やることは残っていました
ベロー兄弟から学ぶべきことが
まだたくさんありました
There was a lot I needed to learn
from Brother Bello.
兄弟は 区域やそこに住む人々のことを
本当によく知っているんです
He really understood
our preaching territory
and the people who live here.
He liked my ideas,
よくできている
と言ってくださったけど—
but everything he showed me
made them even better.
兄弟からのいろいろなアドバイスで
もっといいものができました
I can do a lot
to help the congregation.
会衆のためにたくさんのことができます
And I pray that Jehovah
lets me do even more
そして もっと多くのことができるよう
エホバに祈るんです
with the gifts he gave me
与えられた才能を生かし—
and with the wisdom
of experienced men.
経験ある兄弟の知恵をいただきながら
Ben had good ideas to improve
the work he’d been assigned,
ベンには仕事を改善するための
良い考えがありましたが—
but he also learned to respect
the experience of older brothers.
年長の兄弟の経験を
尊重すべきことも学びました
You too may have ideas
to benefit your assignment,
あなたも 会衆やベテルや
建設プロジェクトでー
whether in the congregation,
at Bethel, or on a construction project.
改善のためのアイデアが
あるかもしれません
Like Ben, seek the wisdom
of experienced brothers and sisters
ベンに倣って
長く割り当てを果たしてきた—
経験ある兄弟や姉妹からの
知恵を求めてください
who did the assignment before you.
Find out why they did things
a certain way.
そのやり方の理由を理解してください
What were the challenges
they faced?
どんな問題に直面したのでしょうか？
What direction and resources
influenced their efforts?
どんな指示や考えに
基づいているでしょうか？
How can their experience
help you succeed?
彼らの経験はどのように
助けになるでしょうか？
You’ll see the wisdom
in what may at first
古臭いと思える方法の中にある
知恵を見いだせるかもしれません
look like outdated methods.
行なわれた仕事について
敬意をもって話し—
Speak respectfully
of their past work,
and you’ll reflect how Jehovah
treasures what they did for Him.
エホバがその仕事を高く評価して
おられることを示すのです
Jehovah will, in turn,
bless the work of your hands.
そうすれば あなたの仕事も
祝福されるでしょう
What else will bring
Jehovah’s blessing?
ほかにも エホバの祝福を
得る方法がありますか？
He draws close
to spiritually-minded people.
エホバは霊的な思いを持つ人に
近づいてくださいます
Young Christians all over the world
are experiencing
神との近しい関係を保つことが—
the benefits of maintaining
a close relationship with God.
世界中の若いクリスチャンたちの
役に立っています
Each of you faces
a unique set of circumstances
皆さんは 霊的な思いを持つ
ことを難しくさせる—
that make it difficult
to be a spiritually-minded youth.
独特の状況に直面しています
So we interviewed young Witnesses
from different lands
それで 世界中の若者たちに
インタビューをして—
to find out what they do
to keep growing spiritually.
霊的成長のために
何をしているかを聞きました
Our relationship with Jehovah
can start when we’re young.
若くても エホバとの友情を
スタートできます
For me, it was the example
that others set
わたしには エホバを第一にして—
of putting Jehovah first
幸せになっている兄弟姉妹たちの
手本がありました
and the happiness
that came as a result,
それがきっかけになって—
as well as being
in that sort of environment
エホバとの友情を築くことに
取り組めました
that really helped me
to want to reach out
もちろん そうできる環境にいた
おかげでもあります
as well as be available
for those opportunities.
一度エホバに自分を差し出すと—
And once we do
give our life to Jehovah,
こんな祝福を取っておいて
くださったんだ と感動するんです
it’s amazing to see the blessings
that he has in store for us.
But in order to build that relationship,
ただ そういう友情を築くには
神の言葉を読んで 祈ることが大切です
we need to read God’s Word;
we also need to pray to him.
The more you
get to know him,
エホバのことが分かってくると
もっとエホバにひかれるようになって—
the more appealing things
you learn about him.
That makes you not want to lose him
as your friend.
友を失いたくないって
思うようになるんです
I always knew it was the truth
自分の信じていることは間違いない—
and that I wanted
to serve Jehovah forever.
エホバのためにずっと
奉仕したいと思っていましたが—
But I needed to reassure myself
of certain aspects,
いくつかの部分で
確信を強める必要がありました
so I did some research projects
with my parents,
それで 両親と「創造者」の本や
「教え」の本を使って調査をしました
using the Creator book and some items
from the Bible Teach book.
そうしたら 信じていることが
はっきりして この生き方をしたい —
After that,
it only became more obvious.
And I was certain that I wanted it
バプテスマを受けたいと
思うようになりました
and that I was ready to get baptized.
To strengthen
my relationship with Jehovah,
エホバともっと親しくなるために—
I read the Bible daily
and I pray.
聖書を毎日読んで祈るようにしています
Especially when
there is no one around or it’s quiet,
周りにだれもいない時や静かな時は
心をこめてエホバに話します
I talk to Jehovah
with all my heart at that time.
エホバへの奉仕を拡大するといっても—
Making myself available
for spiritual opportunities
自分には ちょっと難しいと
感じていました
was a little bit difficult for me at first,
but I didn’t give up.
でも あきらめませんでした
バプテスマを受けてから
奉仕の僕になり—
After my baptism,
I became a ministerial servant,
べテルで2年ほど奉仕しました
and I also served
almost two years in Bethel.
今は正規開拓者として—
And now I’m a regular pioneer
ハパドゥ村にある
カレン語会衆で奉仕しています
in Hpado
in a Karen-speaking congregation.
カレン語のスゴー方言は
全く分からなくて—
I didn’t know or speak
the Karen S’gaw language,
話すこともできませんでしたが—
so the local brothers helped me
to learn not only how to speak
地元の兄弟たちが 読んだり
話したりできるよう教えてくれました
but also how to read.
Prayers
are important to strengthen
エホバともっと親しくなれるよう—
my relationship with Jehovah.
祈りを大切にしています
For me, it’s like talking
友人と話すような時間です
to a friend,
and that’s always helpful.
祈ると エホバが本当に
そこにいると感じますし—
He’s someone real to me,
聞いてくださっていると確信しています
and I fully trust
that he listens to me.
I support the elders by helping
with the cleaning of the hall,
会衆では 案内係や会館の掃除や
マイクを扱う仕事をしながら—
serving as an attendant,
handling microphones,
霊的な面で兄弟姉妹を助けて
長老たちをサポートしています
as well as helping
the congregation spiritually.
When I share Jehovah’s promises
of eternal life with others,
ずっと生きつづけられるという—
エホバの約束について話すと
元気づけられます
I too am encouraged.
エホバの約束をいつも思い出すことが
宣教を続ける力になっています
I’m constantly remembering
what Jehovah promises,
and that motivates me
to keep preaching.
There’s a family
in our congregation
会衆のある家族が
わたしを家に迎え入れて—
who took me into their home
親のようになってくれています
and served
as my spiritual parents.
家族の崇拝があるので—
Through our family worship,
エホバともっと親しくなれるよう
助けられています
they helped me
to progress spiritually.
会衆にいる年長の兄弟姉妹たちの
存在はとても大きいです
The elderly ones in our congregation
have been helping me a lot.
First, they’re good examples.
みんな良いお手本で 思いの焦点を
しっかり合わせておく大切さを教えられます
They also remind me
to keep my eye simple.
Despite their limited circumstances
because of age,
年を取ってできることが
限られていても—
エホバのために働こうと
心に決めているんです
they are determined
to serve Jehovah God.
自分はどうだろう と考えさせられます
And that made me
reflect on my situation.
I’m very young.
兄弟姉妹たちがしているのに—
What prevents me from doing
the things that they do?
若い僕にはできません
なんて言えないです
Before I
began pioneering,
開拓奉仕を始める前は—
I used to sell fish
seven days a week,
週に7日 魚を売って暮らしていました
but now I sell fish four days a week,
so three days are available for pioneering.
それを 週4日に減らしたので—
残りの3日で 開拓奉仕が
できるようになりました
To be able to be available
for spiritual opportunities,
そして エホバのために
もっと奉仕できるよう—
I closely associate
with my congregation.
会衆と関わる機会を
増やすようにしています
I offer some older ones
a ride to the meetings
年配の兄弟姉妹を乗せて
集会や奉仕に行っています
or in the preaching work.
The reason I’m doing this
is because I want to give
自分の若さやエネルギーを
エホバに差し出したいと思っています
my youth and energy
to Jehovah God.
When I was at school,
I would conduct Bible studies
学生のとき 何人かの
クラスメートと研究しました
with some of my classmates.
In time, they joined me
in serving Jehovah.
そして そのクラスメートたちが—
一緒にエホバに奉仕する
仲間になったんです
When I think about being with them
in the future Paradise,
将来 みんなと一緒に
パラダイスにいるんだと思うと—
it gives me deep joy.
本当にうれしい気持ちになります
I have the privilege
of studying with a deaf girl
歩いて2時間のところに—
耳の不自由な女の子が住んでいて
研究ができています
who lives two hours
from where I live.
We have to walk all the way.
彼女は研究を楽しんでいて
家族も協力的です
She is very happy
with what she’s learning,
and her family is very supportive.
エホバが彼女を助け そこに
わたしも関われていると思うと—
So knowing that Jehovah
is helping her
and I have a part in it,
it’s just priceless.
喜びでいっぱいになります
Auxiliary pioneering
definitely helped me
補助開拓奉仕をしたので
開拓奉仕を始める準備ができました
because it was like a stepping stone
to regular pioneering.
The ministry definitely gives you
the opportunity
奉仕に出ると エホバと一緒になって
働くことができます
to be able
to work closely with Jehovah.
そうすると これまで信じてきたことへの
確信がさらに強くなって—
And then it—
By doing that, you’re reaffirming
your faith in what
you already believe in,
and then you’re drawing closer
to Jehovah in friendship.
エホバともっと親しくなれるんです
Having jw.org and the broadcast
jw.orgやBroadcastingがあるので—
has definitely drawn me
closer to our brothers
兄弟姉妹たちやエホバとの距離が
本当に近くなっています
and sisters but also to Jehovah as well.
わたしは内気なほうなので—
Just by nature,
I feel like I’m more of a timid person,
家から家の奉仕をするには
ちょっと勇気がいるんです
so going door to door
can be a little scary.
でも 世界中にいる若い兄弟姉妹が
本当に難しい問題を経験しているのに—
But seeing other young ones
in different parts of the world
that are enduring
very difficult circumstances
エホバに一番良いものを差し出しているのを
見ると勇気がわいてきます
and living conditions
and yet are still giving
their best to Jehovah
is so encouraging for me.
わたしもがんばろう—
エホバに自分のベストを
差し出さなきゃ って思います
And it helps me to keep going on
and give Jehovah my best as well.
When I think personally
about all the avenues of service
個人的に思うことがあるんです
これは どんな奉仕の分野にも
言えると思います
that we can have a hand in today,
エキサイティングな奉仕は
本当にたくさんありますよね
there are so many that are exciting
外国で開拓奉仕をするとか
必要の大きな所での奉仕とか べテル奉仕とか
—whether it be pioneering
in a foreign country,
serving where the need is great,
でも 大事なのは「エホバが善良である
ことを味わい知る」ことなんです
even serving at Bethel.
Unless we “taste and see
that Jehovah is good,”
努力して一度挑戦してみないと—
unless we put ourself out there
エホバへの奉仕はどういうものなのか
本当に知ることは絶対にできません
and are available
to try that at least once,
we’ll never know
what it would be like
やってみて初めて エホバが言って
おられたのはこういう生き方だったんだ
to really serve Jehovah.
And in doing that,
you will see how Jehovah
それが分かるんです
does want the best life for us.
Those young ones
and others like them
これらの若者たちは—
パウロがテモテのうちに見たのと
同じ霊的な特質を育んでいます
are developing the same
spiritual qualities
that Paul saw in Timothy.
Read along with me and see
how Paul described Timothy
ご一緒にフィリピ 2章20節を読んで—
パウロがテモテのことを
どのように述べたかを見てみましょう
at Philippians chapter 2
starting at verse 20:
“For I have no one else
of a disposition like his
“あなた方のことを真に気づかう
彼のような気持ちの者は—”
“わたしにとってほかにいないのです”
“who will genuinely care
for your concerns.
“ほかの者はみな自分の益を求め—”
“For all the others are seeking
their own interests,
“キリスト･イエスの益を
求めていません”
“not those of Jesus Christ.
“しかしあなた方は 彼が実証した
事柄を知っています”
“But you know the proof
he gave of himself,
“that like a child with a father
“つまり 良いたよりを
推し進めるため—”
he slaved with me
to advance the good news.”
“わたしと共に奴隷として
仕えてくれたことです”
What is it that Paul
saw in Timothy?
パウロはテモテのうちに
何を見ましたか？
He saw his spiritual disposition,
or attitude.
霊的な傾向 つまり霊的な態度です
He observed his genuine interest
in his brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹たちへの
真の関心を見て取りました
Timothy really desired
to do God’s will
他の者たちが個人的な関心を
追い求めていても—
テモテは神のご意志を
行なうことを願いました
even though others were seeking
their personal interests.
And Timothy earned
his fellow worshippers’ respect
テモテは宣教で パウロのような経験ある
クリスチャンと共に働くことにより—
by working with older
and more experienced Christians,
仲間の敬意を得ました
like Paul, in the ministry.
When you
spiritually-minded young ones
霊的な思いを持つ若い皆さんが—
cultivate that beautiful
Timothy-like disposition,
テモテのような
素晴らしい特質を培うなら—
エホバの心を喜ばせることができます
you make Jehovah’s heart rejoice.
Of course,
putting Kingdom interests first
もちろん 王国の関心事を第一にして—
and the needs of others
ahead of our own is not always easy.
他の人の必要を自分より優先するのは
簡単ではありません
We know there are real temptations
若者をエホバから引き離してしまう
強い誘惑があるのは確かです
that can lead a young person
away from Jehovah.
When others
outside the congregation
会衆外の人が わたしたちの
能力や才能を認めるようになると—
recognize our abilities
and talents,
we could begin to seek
“great things” for ourselves,
自分のために名声など“大いなること”を
求め始めるかもしれません
perhaps fame and recognition.
In this interview,
Brother Edgardo Franco
インタビューの中で
エドガルド・フランコ兄弟は—
relates how this desire
caused him
この願いが どのようにエホバに
背を向ける原因となったかを話しています
to turn his back on Jehovah.
So, if the Devil tempted Jesus,
サタンは イエスを誘惑しましたから
わたしたちをも誘惑し—
don’t you think
he will try to tempt us
エホバとの関係を危うくさせる可能性が
あるのではないでしょうか？
in order to jeopardize
our relationship with God?
This is the best contract
we’ve ever offered you.
完璧な契約だぞ！
Listen, I’ll get you a plan
集会とやらにはどっかで出られる
so you can attend
your religious meetings during the week.
Just do the concert
for us on the weekend!
とにかく週末はライブだ！
People always ask me,
“音楽業界を引退したのはなぜ？”
とよく聞かれます
“Why did you leave
the music world?”
When I was still a boy,
子どものころ 有名な歌手に
なることを夢見ていました
I had dreams
about becoming a famous singer.
Then I learned the truth,
その後 真理を知っても—
but I never fully removed
those dreams from my heart.
まだ あきらめきれないでいました
And then I started listening
to some bad influences from my past,
やがて 当時の知人が持ってきた
話に乗せられ—
and they got me hooked.
釣り針に引っかかったかのように—
Then they reeled me
into the recording studio.
スタジオに引き寄せられました
The lyrics in the songs
提供された曲の歌詞を見て
かなり良心が痛みました
—they really bothered
my conscience.
リラックスできるように
お酒をもらい—
So they offered me
some liquor to loosen me up,
少し気分が落ち着きました
and then I started
to feel more comfortable.
わたしの唄を聴いて
気に入ったようで—
I started singing,
and they liked what they were hearing.
その曲は国中のラジオ局で
オンエアされました
And those songs ended up
all over the radio stations.
あたかもサタンが エホバを後にした
わたしを表彰したかのようでした
It was as if Satan
gave me a trophy
for abandoning Jehovah.
I became addicted to the applause.
大歓声のとりこになっていました
Everything looks so beautiful,
すべてがきらびやかに見えました
頂点に立つまでは...
but when you’re on top
—when you’re really at the top
of Satan’s world—
サタンの世界での成功に
華やかさなどまったくありません
there’s nothing beautiful there.
I was an actor,
まるで役者...
and when the cameras
turned on,
カメラを見ると スイッチが入り
笑顔を浮かべるんです
my face and my smile
turned on too.
But when I would get back
to the hotel,
でも ホテルに戻ると
落胆がわたしを襲いました
it was a huge letdown.
There was no applause
歓声は消え去り—
—just that silence
that tormented my conscience.
かわりに良心をさいなむ
静寂だけがありました
So basically, you had to find
結局 気を紛らわす
別の方法が必要になり—
other distractions,
and one of those for me
手を出したのがスロットマシンです
was the slot machine.
もちろんカジノに行けば
スロットマシンだけでなく—
And, of course, casinos
don’t just come with slot machines.
それこそ売春や飲酒などにも
身をさらすことになります
They also expose you
to prostitution and alcohol.
My conscience would ask,
内心思っていました
‘What are you doing here?’
“自分はいったい
何をやってるんだ？”
I remember those times on tour,
ツアーに出ていたときのことを
思い出します
from my limousine,
I’d see the brothers preaching,
リムジンの窓から 奉仕をしている姿が
見えて心が打たれました
and that would always touch my heart.
I would say to myself, ‘Wow!
“エホバは自分をあのように
訓練してくれたはずなのに—”
‘Jehovah trained you
to be doing that,
and look at what you’re doing!’
“今 なぜこんなことを...”
と良心がうずきました
That really cut deep into my heart.
The road back to the truth was,
really, very hard.
真理へ戻る道のりは
非常に厳しいものでした
Every time I was going to retire,
I’d say, “This is it!”
引退しようと決めて
これで終わりだ！と思うたびに—
But then there would always be
a bigger contract.
必ず大きな契約がくるんです
I had to make drastic decisions.
思い切った決定が必要でした
But finally I said:
ようやく気づきました
“I don’t care what they offer me.
もう仕事はどうでもいい
エホバのもとへ帰るべきだ
“I have to return to Jehovah.
“I have to fulfill the vow
若い頃にエホバと交わした
献身の誓いを全うしなければいけないと
“I made to him
when I was a young man,
when I dedicated my life to him.”
真剣にこうエホバに祈りました
So I prayed to Jehovah
very earnestly and said:
“エホバ あなたのもとへ—”
“Jehovah,
I need to return to you.
“あなたの腕の中へ
帰らせてください”
“I need to return
to your loving arms.
“サタンがあなたから
引き離しました”
“Satan has ripped me
away from you.
“どうか 助けてください”
Please help me.”
最初の集会に出席する前に
エホバに祈りました
I remember that before I went
in to that first meeting,
“わたしを連れ戻してくださる
という証拠を見せてください”
I told Jehovah, “Please give me a sign
that you will take me back.”
会場に入ると
一人の年配の姉妹が歩み寄り—
And there was
an elderly sister there.
She gave me a great big hug
わたしをしっかりと抱きしめて
“お帰り”と言ってくれました
and said, “Welcome back, son!”
そして わたしの手を取り—
And she took my hand
集会中ずっとわたしと一緒に
座ってくれたのです
and sat by me
during the entire meeting.
I had betrayed Jehovah,
but I thank—
エホバを裏切っていました
でも エホバは...
I thank the brothers
長老たちを通して—
because Jehovah
put brothers at every turn.
どんな時でも助けてくださいました
They showed me with the Bible
わたしがどれほど真理の道から
それてしまっているか—
how far I had strayed
でも 行なうことで結果はついてくると
聖書から示してくれました
from the paths of the true God,
and everything you do
has consequences.
I have asked Jehovah many times
to forgive me for all the things
今までしてきたことや 自分の行ないで
傷つけてしまったすべての人に対して—
I have done
—and the brothers too—
all the people
I offended by my actions.
何度もエホバに許しを願い求めました
All those trophies I won
これまで手にした
賞やトロフィーはすべて—
—every last one of them—
ほこりにまみれた
無意味なものです
are there collecting dust.
But Jehovah has given me
それに引き換えエホバは—
a different kind of trophy
in his organization
人々を真理の道へ導くという
特別な賞を与えてくださいました
—helping others to dedicate
their lives to him.
That’s something no one
can take away from you.
それは 誰も取り去ることの
できないものです
We don’t all
have to learn the hard way.
必ずしも辛い経験は必要ありませんが
忍耐は必要です
We have to keep enduring
and never turn
our backs on Jehovah.
エホバに背くことは
誰もが犯し得る最悪のあやまちです
That’s the worst mistake
anyone could make.
We know that it’s Jehovah
who gives us our talents,
エホバが
才能を授けてくださったのですから—
so we should use them
all in his service.
それをエホバへの奉仕に使うべきです
I have found happiness,
and that gives me
真の幸福を見いだしたので—
カメラの前でも演技はしていません
a glow that’s not just
for the cameras.
Everyone who knows me
can see it.
わたしを知るみなさんが
よく知っています
フランコ兄弟は 正規開拓者また
会衆の長老として奉仕を楽しんでいます
Brother Franco enjoys serving
as both a regular pioneer
and congregation elder.
He feels privileged
to shepherd young people
兄弟は 自分と同様の誘惑に
直面している若者をー
facing some of the same temptations
he experienced.
牧羊できることを
うれしく思っています
He often relates a favorite scripture
from Proverbs 8:35.
兄弟は箴言 8章35節の
聖句についてよく話します
Referring to wisdom,
that scripture says:
その聖句は知恵について—
“For the one finding me
will find life,
“わたしを見いだす者は
必ず命を見いだしー”
“エホバから善意を得る”
と述べています
and he receives approval
from Jehovah.”
Brothers and sisters,
兄弟姉妹たち—
エホバは わたしたちが命を見いだし
霊的な物事を探求する点で—
Jehovah does want us to find life,
and he wants us to be successful
in our spiritual pursuits.
成功するようにと願っておられます
In this Bethel morning worship,
ベテルの朝の崇拝で
ロバート・ルシオーニ兄弟は—
Brother Robert Luccioni
discusses how we can reach
自分の可能性をどうすれば最大限
発揮できるかについて述べています
the potential that Jehovah knows
we have.
Our text today is very encouraging
as it reminds us,
今日の聖句は大きな励みとなります
through this example of Amos,
アモスの例から分かるように—
that Jehovah notices the potential
エホバはご自分の僕一人一人の
可能性をご存じです
of each one of his servants.
In fact, one of the comments
from today’s text states:
ある注解はこう述べています
“Even though we may
lack self-confidence,
“自分に自信がなくても エホバは—”
“Jehovah can help us
go beyond our perceived limits
“これまで考えてもみなかったことが
行なえるよう助けてくださるのです”
and reach goals that we
would not have imagined.”
See, Jehovah knows our potential.
そうです エホバは
わたしたちの可能性をご存じです
But you note from that statement,
しかし この言葉から
可能性を発揮するためには—
this is also a reminder
that we have to put forth effort
努力が求められることも分かります
to reach our potential.
You see, if we’re not careful,
we can sabotage our own efforts
エホバは可能性を見ておられるのに—
注意しないと それを発揮する
努力を怠りかねません
to reach the potential
that Jehovah sees in us.
どうしてそんなことが
あり得るでしょうか？
How’s that possible?
Well, let’s look at three examples.
三つの例を考えましょう
Number one:
We can limit potential
一つ目です
務めに打ち込まないなら
可能性を狭めてしまいます
by not throwing ourselves
into what we are asked to do.
Now, we may remember
the account of Jehoash
列王第二 13章にある
イスラエルの王—
the king of Israel
there in 2 Kings chapter 13,
エホアシュについての
記述をご存じでしょう
when he visited
the prophet Elisha who was dying.
彼は 死を目前にした
預言者エリシャのもとを訪ねました
And you notice there
at 2 Kings 13:17
列王第二 13章17節で エリシャは
エホアシュの可能性をこう述べています
that Elisha
notes Jehoash’s potential.
You notice he says there
that: “You will
“あなたは必ずやシリアを
徹底的に討ち倒すであろう”
strike down Syria . . .
until you finish it off.”
See, he noted the potential
シリアを徹底的に打ち倒す
可能性に言及しました
that he had to finish off Syria.
But then what happens?
でも どうなりますか？
Well, you remember that’s where
Elisha tells the king
王は 矢で地を打つよう
エリシャに指示されますが—
3回しかそうしませんでした
to beat the arrows
on the ground three times or—
beat it on the ground,
and he only does it three times.
19節をご覧ください
Notice what happens in verse 19:
“すると まことの神の人は彼に対して
憤慨した ゆえに彼は言った”
“At that the man of the true God
“grew indignant at him and said:
“‘You should have struck the ground
five or six times!
“「五回か六回打つべきであった！”
“そうであれば あなたは確かに
シリアを徹底的に討ち倒したであろう”
“‘Then you
would have struck down Syria
“‘until you finished it off,
“‘but now
you will strike down Syria
“だが 今や あなたがシリアを
討ち倒すのは三度であろう」”
only three times.’”
What happened?
どうしてこうなったのでしょうか？
Well, you see, by not throwing himself
into what he was asked to do
務めに打ち込まず
熱意が欠けていたため—
—showing zeal for his assignment—
成功は限られたのです
he would only
have limited success.
エホアシュは自ら自分の可能性を
狭めてしまいました
Jehoash limited his own potential.
Number two:
We can limit our potential
2番目です
by focusing on our inadequacies
or our insecurities.
自分の欠点や
自信のなさに注意を向けると—
可能性を狭めてしまいます
The account that drives that home
for me is that of Moses.
出エジプト記 3章で
モーセは熱意はありましたが—
If you look in Exodus chapter 3,
and in this account we know
it’s not due to lack of zeal,
自信のなさゆえに
エホバに用いていただける機会を—
but, rather,
Moses’ own insecurities
危うく逃すところでした
that nearly caused him to limit
how he was used by Jehovah.
So we know in Exodus chapter 3,
モーセはファラオの前に出る
という重責を受けました
he received a very weighty assignment
—going to Pharaoh.
And notice what happens
in verse 11,
11節のモーセの言葉に
注目してください
Exodus 3:11.
It says: “However,
Moses said to the true God:
“「一体この私が何者だというので
ファラオのもとに行ったり—”
“‘Who am I that I
should go to Pharaoh
“イスラエルの子らをエジプトから—”
“導き出したりすることに
なるのでしょうか」”
and bring the Israelites
out of Egypt?’”
Now, that’s a normal reaction.
これは普通の反応で だれもが—
We probably would have felt
the same way.
“エホバ 本当にわたしですか？”
と思うでしょう
‘Jehovah, are you sure
you have the right person here?’
And Jehovah says, ‘No.
I do.
エホバは “本当です わたしが共にいます”
とおっしゃいます
I will be with you.’
You look on in verse 13, it says:
13節—
“わたしが今イスラエルのもとに行って—”
“But Moses said to the true God:
‘Suppose I
“「あなた方の父祖の神がわたしを遣わした」
と言うとしても—”
“‘go to [Israel] and say to them,
“‘“The God of your forefathers
has sent me to you,”
“「その方の名は何というのか」
と彼らが言うとすれば—”
“‘and they say to me,
“What is his name?”
“何と言えばよいでしょうか”
What should I say to them?’”
Jehovah says, ‘No problem,’
and He explains His name
エホバは “大丈夫”と言って
お名前の意味や後ろ盾について説明されます
—even tells him
what His name means
and how that power
will be behind him.
Chapter 4, verse 1:
4章1節—
“However, Moses answered:
‘But suppose they do not believe me
“「ですが 彼らがわたしを信じず—”
“わたしの声に聴き従わない
ならばどうでしょうか」”
“‘and do not listen to my voice,
for they will say,
“Jehovah did not appear to you.”’”
エホバは “大丈夫
その手にあるのは何ですか？”—
‘No problem, Moses.
What’s in your hand?’
It’s where he has the staff.
と言って 杖を用い
後ろ盾を示す奇跡を見せます
He shows him miracles
that he can perform to show
that Jehovah is behind him.
Look at verse 10:
10節—
“Moses now said to Jehovah:
‘Pardon me, Jehovah,
“「お許しください エホバよ—”
“私は流ちょうに
話せる者ではございません”
“‘but I have never been a fluent speaker,
neither in the past
“私は口が重いのです」”
“‘nor since you have spoken
to your servant,
for I am slow of speech
and slow of tongue.’”
エホバは “誰が口を造りましたか？”
‘OK, Moses,
who created the mouth?
“わたしが話します 心配ありません”
と言われます
I’ll speak for you.
Don’t worry about it.’
Look at verse 13:
13節—
“But he said: ‘Pardon me,
Jehovah, please send
“「どうか あなたが遣わそうと
しておられる者の手によって—”
anyone whom you
want to send.’”
“お遣わしになりますように」”
And notice what it says
in verse 14:
14節—
“Then Jehovah’s anger
blazed against Moses.”
“するとエホバの怒りは
モーセに対して燃えた”
‘Fine, you know, I’m going
to just send somebody else.’
“分かった 誰かを遣わしましょう”
But, you see, thankfully,
Moses got the point
幸いここでモーセは要点をつかみ—
and he jumped into the assignment
and was used further by Jehovah.
割り当てを受け入れ 用いられました
But what happened here?
でもモーセは 自分の欠点にとらわれ
失敗を心配しすぎていたのです
You notice, Moses got caught up
worrying about his inadequacies,
worrying about all the things
that could go wrong.
エホバは “ともかく進み あとは任せなさい”
と言っておられました
Jehovah was saying,
‘Just get moving,
and I will take care
of the rest.’
エホバは 割り当てを果たせると
見ておられましたが—
Jehovah saw that
Moses had the potential
to carry out this assignment;
モーセは 自分に限度を設けていました
however,
Moses was limiting himself.
Number three:
We can limit our own potential
3番目です—
失敗を恐れて萎縮し
可能性を自分で狭めることがあります
by becoming paralyzed by fear
—fear of failure.
If you turn to the account
in Numbers chapter 13,
民数記 13章には 10人の
スパイに生じたことが書かれています
we notice that this
is what happened to the ten spies.
And it’s very interesting,
偵察後の彼らの言葉に注目しましょう
a phrase they used when they
came back from spying out the land.
Numbers chapter 13,
and look at verse 33.
民数記 13章33節です
It says:
“And there we saw the Nephilim,
“そして そこでネフィリムを見た”
“ネフィリムから出たアナクの子らだ”
“the sons of Anak,
who [were] from the Nephilim,
“そのためわたしたちは—”
ここに注目します
and in comparison
we seemed like grasshoppers,”
“自分の目にはばったのようになり
彼らの目にもそのようになった”
and notice, “both to us
and to them.”
You see, they ran into these
sons of Anak who were giants,
カナンの山地に住む巨人
アナクの子らに会った時—
men of extraordinary size
who inhabited
エホバの敵が イスラエル人を
ちっぽけな ばったのように—
the mountainous region of Canaan,
and it was understandable
that these enemies of Jehovah
“簡単に踏みつぶせる
相手にもならない”—
viewed the Israelites
as puny grasshoppers.
そうみなしたのは理解できます
‘You can just squash them
—no competition.’
But, you know, the ten spies
しかし 10人のスパイも
自分自身を同じように見てしまいました
saw themselves the same way.
And, see, their view
of themselves in this situation
その見方のために恐れで萎縮し—
paralyzed them with fear
and caused them
国民全体の士気を
くじいてしまったのです
to demoralize the entire nation.
But now, in contrast,
we think of the account of David,
対照的に 若い時に巨人ゴリアテと
対決したダビデについて考えましょう
who as a young man
also encountered a giant, Goliath.
And remember, Goliath also saw David
as a defenseless little boy
ゴリアテも ダビデをばったのような
か弱い少年と見なしました
and as a grasshopper,
if you will.
でも ダビデは自分を
そのように見ましたか？
But did David see himself
the same way?
いいえ “あなたは剣と槍とを持って
わたしに向かって来るが—”
No, he said: ‘You are coming to me
with sword and spear.
I am coming to you
with the name of Jehovah.’
“わたしはエホバのみ名をもって
あなたに向かって行く”と言い—
You see, David did not allow himself
to be paralyzed by fear.
恐れのために萎縮しませんでした
He trusted in Jehovah,
and David lived up to the potential
エホバを信頼し エホバがご覧になった
可能性に沿って行動したのです
that Jehovah saw in him.
So, what’s the lesson for us?
教訓は何でしょうか？
Well, the lesson is that this illustrates
時として 自分自身が
最大の敵となり得ます
—these accounts illustrate—
that sometimes we can be
our own worst enemy at times.
See, lack of zeal
—not throwing ourself into the work,
エホアシュのような
熱意の欠けた中途半端な取り組み方—
as in the case of Jehoash;
or our own insecurities,
as in the case of Moses;
モーセのような自信のなさ—
10人のスパイのような失敗への恐れは—
or fear of failure,
as in the case of the ten spies
エホバがわたしたちのうちに
見ておられる可能性を狭めてしまいます
—can cause us to limit
the potential that Jehovah sees in us.
So, what do we do?
では どうすべきでしょうか？
Well, Jehovah’s words to Gideon
remind us of what we could do,
ギデオンに対する
エホバの言葉から分かります
裁き人 6章をご覧ください
and we invite you
to turn to Judges chapter 6.
And you remember
that for seven years
ミディアン人は
イスラエルを7年間圧迫していました
the Midianites
oppressed the nation of Israel,
エホバのみ使いはギデオンに現れ—
and Jehovah’s angel appears
to Gideon and says that He is going
ギデオンがイスラエルを
邪悪な国民から救い出すと言いました
to deliver Israel
out of this wicked nation.
How could he possibly succeed?
どうしてそんなことが
できるのでしょう？
We read the account,
and Gideon saw himself
ギデオンは 自分が父の家の中で
最も小さな者であり—
as the least significant
one of his father’s house.
自分の父の家はマナセの部族の中で
最も小さな家族であると言いました
And he said his father’s house
was the least significant family
of the tribe of Manasseh.
But yet Jehovah saw
the potential that Gideon had.
それでも エホバはギデオンの
可能性を見ておられました
And what did Jehovah
tell him to do?
何をするように言われたでしょうか？
Look at Judges 6:14.
裁き人 6章14節を見ましょう
It says:
“Jehovah faced him and said:
“それに対しエホバは
彼に面と向かってこう言った—”
“‘Go with the strength you have,
“「あなたのこの力をもって
出かけて行きなさい”
“‘and you will save Israel
out of Midian’s hand.
“あなたはイスラエルを必ず
ミディアンの掌中から救うことになる”
Is it not I who [sent] you?’”
“わたしがあなたを
遣わしたのではないか」”
Interesting.
興味深い言葉です
‘Go with the strength
you have.
“あなたのこの力をもって
出かけて行きなさい”
‘I know you cannot do it
on your own strength.
“あなた自身の力で
できないことは知っています”
‘Just get moving;
throw everything you can into it;
“とにかく進み
できることは何でも行ないなさい！”
and I, Jehovah,
will make up the difference.’
“そうすれば わたしエホバが
足りないところを補おう”
You see,
that’s what Jehovah is saying,
and that’s exactly what happened.
そして そのとおりになりました
So may we be determined
to do the same.
わたしたちも同じ決意を抱きましょう
We know that none of us
accomplish Jehovah’s work
自分の力 知恵 能力で
エホバの務めを果たせる人はいません
on our own strength,
on our own wisdom,
on our own abilities.
それでも 割り当てを受けたら
とにかく進みましょう
But when we receive an assignment,
we need to just start moving.
Do not let our inadequacies
paralyze us.
自信のなさや 失敗への恐れで
萎縮してはなりません
Do not let fear of failure
paralyze us.
熱意を持ち 打ち込みましょう
Throw ourselves into the work.
Have a zeal for the work.
自分のこの力をもって
出かけて行くのです
Go with the strength
that you have.
エホバが足りない点を
補ってくださることを確信してください
Trust in Jehovah
to make up the difference,
そうすれば エホバがあなたに見ておられる
可能性に沿って行動できるでしょう
and you will live up to the potential
that Jehovah sees in you.
What excellent counsel for all of us,
and especially for young ones
わたしたち皆にとって—
特に若者にとって
なんと素晴らしい助言でしょう
with a life of service to God
ahead of them.
若者たちの前途にはエホバに仕える
人生があり それは永遠に続くのです
That life with Jehovah
can be everlasting!
That is our firm hope.
それは確かな希望です！
Until then, will you remain loyal,
それまで 忠節を保ち
世が提供する物を退け—
resist what the world offers you,
and reach your potential?
可能性を最大限発揮しますか？
Imagine your life
100 years from now.
100年後の自分を
想像してみてください
Will you regret the decades
you gave to Jehovah?
エホバのために用いた数十年を
後悔しますか？
Will anything you endured
in Satan’s system
サタンの体制下で何かを我慢しても—
それが 命の賞を得る妨げに
なるでしょうか？
slow you down
from gaining life’s prize?
Some of our brothers and sisters
can already look back
兄弟姉妹たちの中には
以前のことを振り返り—
that far and answer
those questions.
その質問に答えられる人がいます
Sister Alma Miller’s family
learned the truth
アルマ・ミラー姉妹の家族は
彼女が10歳の時に真理を学びました
when she was ten years old.
She was baptized in 1937
姉妹は 1937年にバプテスマを受け
今 107歳です
and is now 107 years old.
To her, just about everyone
is a young person.
彼女にとってはすべての人が若者です
See the encouraging effect
her loving and faithful example
姉妹の愛すべき忠実な模範が—
会衆の若者たちに及ぼしている
励みある影響に注目してください
has on young ones
in her congregation.
People often tell me,
皆さんはよくこう言います
“Why, I never talked to a person
“これまで107歳の人と
話したことはないわ”
that was 107 years old.”
それで わたしもこう言います
“そう わたしもないわ”
And I tell them,
“You know what?
I never did either.”
I would describe Alma
アルマはこれまでに会った
100歳以上の女性の中で—
as probably the most energetic
たぶん一番活力があると思います
100-plus-year-old lady
that I’ve ever met.
She has, pretty much,
アルマはこれまでの神権的な出来事を
よく覚えています
the whole theocratic history
in her mind that she carries with her.
だから組織について尋ねると
何でも答えてくれます
So you can ask her anything
about the organization,
and she can be able to tell you about it
because she’s even met
a lot of those people.
実際に会った人々のことですから
We read about it, but she lived it.
She’s amazing.
わたしたちは読んで学びますが
アルマはそれを経験したんです
107歳ですが
素晴らしい記憶力です
Even though she’s 107,
she has an incredible memory.
I go back quite a ways.
今でもよく覚えています
When I was very young,
ten years old,
まだ 若い10歳のころだったかしら
we saw the “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
「創造の写真劇」を見たのよ
たくさんの人が来ていて—
And it was just packed with people.
後ろで立っている人もいたわ
They were even standing in the back.
感動的でした
今でも忘れていません
We were so thrilled.
We never forgot it.
そして 真理を見つけたと思いました
And we realized
that we found the truth.
My father left the church
父は教会を去り
エホバの証人になりました
and he became
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
当時は 聖書研究者と
呼ばれていました
and they were called Bible Students
at that time.
In the early days,
we went to special conventions,
初期のころ 特別大会に行きました
and some places,
they had a big field
そして そこにあった
広い場所に車を止めて—
where they put the cars
and they set up their tents.
自分たちのテントを張りました
They even named different streets.
通路には通りの名前までつけました
It was just like a little city.
ちょっとした町のようでした
I was really thrilled
to see Brother Rutherford speak
大会でラザフォード兄弟が話すのを見て
胸がわくわくしました
at the conventions I attended.
I got married to Harold Miller in 1931.
1931年にハロルド・ミラーと
結婚しました
That was when the depression
was going on,
それは大恐慌の最中で
とても厳しい時代でした
and times were very difficult.
Everything was scarce.
物のほとんどない時代でした
There were no jobs to be had.
仕事もありませんでした
Food was rationed.
食料は配給制で みんな空腹でした
People were really hungry.
And they moved in any little shack
そして—
どんな掘っ立て小屋に移ってでも
なんとか暮らしていこうとしました
that they could just to get by.
何も持っていませんでした
We didn’t have anything.
車は運転できませんでしたが—
And we couldn’t drive the car,
ルーという名のかわいい白い馬を
持っていました
so we used to have a little white horse
—the name was Lou.
その馬と馬車で奉仕に出かけました
And we went out witnessing
with the horse and buggy.
あらゆる場所に出かけ
ずいぶん遠くにも行きました
She took us all over the place,
far distances.
They would take this buggy,
and they would go
彼らはその馬車を使って こちらに数十キロ—
20-30 miles in one direction;
あちらに数十キロと出かけていきました
20-30 miles the other direction.
All the hard work that they put forth
そうした努力の結果 この地域には
いくつもの会衆が存在しています
has resulted
in several congregations in the area.
We used to carry that magazine bag
そこで奉仕した しばらくの間
この雑誌のバッグをよく使いました
when we were witnessing
for awhile there.
馬の首の周りにそれをつけたので
馬も証言に加わったことになります
And so we put it
around the horse’s neck,
so the horse was taking part
in our witnessing.
白い馬が庭にやってくるのを見ると
家の人はだれが来たかが分かりました
People knew
who was coming when they saw
the little white horse
come into their yard.
あまりにも寒い時には
コートを2枚着たこともあります
Sometimes it was cold,
and I remember wearing two coats.
Yeah, it was tiresome,
確かに大変でしたけど...
若かったんですね
but we were young.
They would just go out
regardless of rain or shine
降っても照っても何があっても
出かけたんですね
or whatever was going on at the time,
and they didn’t have a car.
車もなかったのにです
すごいと思います
And to me, that’s amazing
because we get so used to
わたしたちは便利なものに
慣れていますよね
the conveniences
—I guess you could call it—
コーヒーショップとか 車とかです
the coffee breaks,
the cars, and everything.
アルマと同じようにできるかも
っていう気持ちです
It’s like, well,
if Alma can do it, surely I can do it.
One time,
Harold went out witnessing,
ある時 ハロルドは証言に出かけましたが
50年後 同じ人に会いました
and 50 years later,
he talked to the same man.
He said, “50 years ago,
その人はこう言いました
“50年前 一人の若者が
白い馬に乗ってやって来て—”
“there was a young guy
that came through here
“riding on horseback
“人々にこんなことを
言っていましたよ”
and telling people that,”
he said,
“確か「アルマギゴン」
と言っていたと思いますが—”
“I think it’s ‘Armaggigon,’
he said was coming soon.”
”それが近づいている
ということでした”
And he remembered
Harold riding horseback
その人はハロルドがそこで—
50 years ago in that territory,
50年前に馬に乗っていたことを
覚えていたんですね
and he got there again.
And that happened
a couple times more.
そうしたことは数回ありました
So it was a long life of witnessing.
それは生涯にわたる証言ですね
Alma is so zealous for the ministry.
アルマは宣教にとても熱心です
She does not like not-at-homes.
だから留守宅は嫌いです
家の人と話したいのです
She wants to talk to people.
Yeah, I enjoy the ministry.
奉仕が大好きです
I go out as much as I can
in my old age.
年を取っていても
できるだけ出かけます
We want to help the people
to see the truth.
真理を理解するよう助けたいです
There’s no greater joy.
この上ない喜びです
I try to read the publications,
出版物を読むときには
読書装置を使います
so I have a reading machine.
The letters come right out of the screen,
画面に文字が出るので
資料をよく学ぶことができます
and I can study all my lessons.
これは大きな助けです
I would be lost without it.
おかげでいつも
真理を語る準備ができます
It helps me to keep up
in present truth.
What does dedication mean?
献身とは 何を意味しますか？
ミラー姉妹
Sister Miller, please.
Dedication means that. . .
献身とは……
人生で何をすべきか
どんな選択をすべきか—
Some young ones might be concerned
about what they should do
with their life,
what choices they should make.
心配する若者がいますが—
Well, here we see an example
of somebody who has served Jehovah
ここに100年以上
エホバに仕えてきた人の模範があります
for over 100 years.
And we see that she’s happy
and has no regrets with her life.
アルマは幸福で 後悔などしていません
見倣うべき模範です
And that’s an example
that we want to imitate.
Well, giving my life to Jehovah,
エホバに命をささげることは
自分で行なえる最善の事柄です
that’s the best thing
I could do for myself.
If I have any advice
for young ones today,
今の若い人に
アドバイスをするとしたら—
I would say
to keep on in the truth.
真理に留まり続けるように勧めます
若者の前途には エホバに仕える
ための素晴らしい世界があります
They have a whole world before them
to serve Jehovah
それは 永遠に続きます
—something that endures forever.
Wasn’t that encouraging?
励まされますね
With all the videos we use
in our worship today,
今日 崇拝において
ビデオを用いていますが—
it’s also interesting that
Sister Miller’s introduction to the truth
ミラー姉妹が真理に接したのが—
「創造の写真劇」だったのは
興味深いことです
was the “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
That was a photographic slide
and motion picture production,
それは カラースライドと動画と音声を
組み合わせたもので—
complete with color and sound,
which first showed in 1914.
1914年に最初に上映されました
You might enjoy learning more
about that historic presentation
その歴史的な上映について—
個人研究でさらに
調べてみることができるでしょう
as a personal study project.
Sister Miller has experienced
much in her 107 years.
ミラー姉妹は107年の間に
多くの経験をしました
She’s endured economic depression,
health problems,
経済恐慌 健康の問題 愛する夫を含む
家族や友人との別れなどです
and the loss of family and friends,
including her dear husband.
But as we saw,
Jehovah has blessed her
しかし エホバは姉妹を—
会衆の霊的な家族をもって
祝福されました
with a spiritual family
in the congregation.
同時に ミラー姉妹と一緒に
インタビューされた人々は—
At the same time,
those interviewed with Sister Miller
年配者との近しい交友を
楽しんでいます
are enjoying a close friendship
with someone older.
Even very young ones
are finding friends
かなり若い人でも 年上の兄弟姉妹の中に
友人を見いだしています
among older brothers and sisters.
David, age nine, wrote this
in his letter to the Governing Body:
9歳になるデービッドは
統治体に宛てて—
“ぼくは大人の人の話を聴くのが
好きです“と書きました
“I like to listen to older ones.
“I just used to have
a circle of friends,
“ぼくには友だちが
たくさんいましたが—”
but now I feel more comfortable
going and talking to older ones.”
“いまは大人の人と話す方が
ずっといいです”
It’s no surprise, then,
「エホバの友になろう」の
最新のビデオの中で—
that in the latest
Become Jehovah’s Friend video,
若くても年を取っていても
友だちになれることを—
Sophia learns that you’re never
too young
ソフィアが学んだのは
驚くことではありません
or too old
to be someone’s friend.
Sister Elsa,
エルサ姉妹
みんな姉妹が描いたの？
did you paint these?
I did.
そうよ
They’re amazing!
すごい！どうして描いたんですか？
How long
have you been drawing?
As long as I can remember.
これまでのいろんな経験を
みんなに伝えたいと思って—
It’s my way
of being able to share
all the stories of my life.
絵にしてきたの
Could you show me?
聞いてみたい
Yes, of course!
もちろん いいわよ
若いころ 東ドイツにいたの
I remember a time when I was young
and in East Germany.
エホバの証人の活動が
許されていなかった
We weren’t allowed to do our work
as Jehovah’s Witnesses;
we were under ban.
禁令下でね
ものみの塔を書き写す
お手伝いをしたのよ
I helped in copying
our Watchtower magazines by hand
それを食料の中に隠して
and then hiding them in food.
You did?
へーっ
Yes!
刑務所にいる兄弟たちに
それを届ける役だったの
We’d then send the food
to our brothers who were in prison.
I was also asked to help
in distributing Bible literature
あちこちの会衆に
霊的な食物を配る仕事をしたわ
to our congregations
as an underground messenger.
見つからないように注意しながらね
ワーっ
Wow!
Time passed and then things
started getting better in Berlin.
その後 ベルリンの状況が
だんだん良くなったの
しばらくしてから
ニューヨークに引っ越して—
Shortly after,
I immigrated to New York.
そこで素敵な人に会えた
それが主人よ
And I met my darling husband.
Wow, that was a great story!
とってもいいお話ですね
Thank you.
ありがと
But I’m sure you have stories.
あなたもいっぱいお話あるでしょ
What do you like to draw?
どんな絵を描くの？
Well, actually, here!
あっ ここにあります
This was the time
when Caleb and I went to the park,
カレブと公園に行って
そこで女の子に会った時の絵です…
and we met a little girl there.
エルサ姉妹のところに行って
楽しかったです
I’m glad I reached out that day.
Lasting friends can be of any age
when they love Jehovah.
エホバを愛していれば—
年が離れていても
本当の友達になれるんです
Elsa and Sophia already share
much in common
エルサとソフィアには
すでに共通点がたくさんあり—
良い友になれそうな気がします
and are likely
to become good friends.
We’re pleased to announce that
うれしいことに—
「エホバの友になろう」の
この新しいビデオは—
this new Become Jehovah’s Friend lesson
is available
ビデオ・オンデマンドの「子ども向け」
のカテゴリーから入手できます
on Video on Demand
under the “Children” category.
You parents and family heads
親や家族の頭の皆さんは
できることを行なって—
are doing all you can
to teach your children from infancy
子どもたちが幼い時からエホバを愛し
その友となるよう教えています
to love Jehovah
and to become his friend.
As they grow,
you also teach them
成長に伴って 子どもたちが
自分で学び 祈るように教えます
how to study and pray
on their own.
You know they need
these spiritual skills.
子どもたちはこれらを
身に着ける必要があります
Young ones, remember that
your personal study time
若い皆さん 個人研究の時間は
自分が経験している事について—
is when you
can ask Jehovah for help
エホバからの助けをいただける時間
であることを 忘れないでください
with what you
are personally experiencing,
その研究の時間は
ほかにも良い益をもたらします
and that study time
has other good effects.
As this music video tells us,
今月のミュージック・ビデオは
“水辺の木のように”というものです
“Study Makes You Strong”!
あの頃は パパに抱かれ
Since we could crawl,
our family studied it all.
家族で読む エホバの手紙
Even though small,
we understood what we were learning.
おやすみ前の おたのしみ
Father would read to me
before I would sleep.
今では ほら わたしのルーティーン
Now I am taller;
I still keep up with that routine.
開いたことば ページから取り出し
And when I’m by myself,
I take that book down off the shelf.
心に置けば 昨日よりも強くなれる
I remember what the scripture said
that I would need so I could stand firm.
(Study makes you strong)
水辺で生きる木のように
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
by a river stream.
(Study makes you strong)
渇きを知らず 高く高く
Study makes you strong.
Your leaves just won’t dry out
and everything succeeds.
(Study makes you strong)
深く根を伸ばす木のように
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
its roots down deep.
(Study makes you strong)
大地を つかんで  離さない
Study makes you strong.
You’ll grow so big and tall
there’s nothing you won’t see.
目の前に チャンス来たら
What will I say when a big chance
comes my way?
クラスメイトに うまく 言えるかな？
What will my classmates say
if I don’t follow with them?
ひとりきりでも 恐れずに
All of the information’s
here on display.
見つかる ほら ヒントは ここに
I’m not afraid,
because I learned this as an infant.
開いたことば ページから取り出し
ʹCause when I’m by myself,
I take that book down off the shelf.
心に置けば 昨日よりも強くなれる
I remember what the scripture said
that I would need so I could stand firm.
(Study makes you strong)
水辺で生きる木のように
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
by a river stream.
(Study makes you strong)
渇きを知らず  実らせてく
Study makes you strong.
Your leaves just won’t dry out
and everything succeeds.
(Study makes you strong)
深く根を伸ばす木のように
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
its roots down deep.
(Study makes you strong)
優しく みんなを包み込む
Study makes you strong.
You’ll grow so big and tall
there’s nothing you won’t see.
すべてのことばに
Every word that’s helping me
Could contain the very key
とびら開く鍵がある
あなたのため 今すぐ伝えたい
To offer just the help
and encouragement somebody needs.
Study makes you strong.
Study makes you strong
(Study makes you strong)
水辺で生きる木のように
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
by a river stream.
(Study makes you strong)
渇きを知らず輝いてく
Study makes you strong.
Your leaves just won’t dry out
and everything succeeds.
(Study makes you strong)
深く根を伸ばす木のように
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
its roots down deep.
(Study makes you strong)
強く 大空に手を伸ばし
Study makes you strong.
You’ll grow so big and tall
there’s nothing you won’t see.
Study does make us strong!
研究によって木のように強くなれます！
As depicted in the music video,
the Bible reading and study habits
ミュージックビデオで
描かれていたように—
若い姉妹が家族と一緒に始めた—
that the young sister
started with her family
聖書通読と研究の習慣は
自分の習慣になりました
became her own personal habits.
When a challenging situation or opportunity
to give a witness came along,
難しい状況や証言の機会が訪れた時—
姉妹は 必要な情報を
聖書から探す方法をすでに知っていました
she already knew how to research
what she needed from the Scriptures.
Our prayer is that all of you
young brothers and sisters
わたしたちの願いは—
若い兄弟姉妹たちが同様の仕方で
霊的に強くなり—
grow spiritually strong
in the same way
世界中にいる忠実な者たちの
模範となることです
and become examples
to faithful ones everywhere.
That brings us
to our video postcard
では 忠実な兄弟姉妹からの
ビデオ・ポストカードをご覧ください
from faithful brothers and sisters.
今月は 中央ヨーロッパの美しい国
オーストリアを訪問します
This month we visit beautiful Austria,
in Central Europe.
C・T・ラッセル兄弟は1891年に
初めてオーストリアを訪問しました
Brother C.T. Russell
first visited Austria in 1891.
He returned in 1911 to plant
兄弟は首都ウイーンで
さらに王国の種をまくため—
further seeds of Kingdom truth
in the capital city, Vienna.
1911年に再びそこを訪問しました
Today, there are more than 21,000
active publishers
今日 人口800万人のオーストリアに
2万1千人以上の活発な伝道者がいます
among the eight million
who live in Austria.
One of the 301 congregations
301ある会衆のうちの一つが
ウデーンにあるドイツ語の会衆です
is the German-language congregation
in Uderns.
They preach in a territory
of alpine mountains and valleys.
兄弟たちはアルプスの山や谷を
区域として奉仕します
Some farms are as high in elevation
as 1,700 meters,
いくつかの農場が
海抜1700メートルの所に散在しています
or more than 5,500 feet.
困難な地形にも関わらず
王国の音信の速度は落ちていません
But difficult terrain does not slow
the Kingdom message.
The 48 publishers there
最近48人の伝道者は
51件の聖書研究を報告しました
recently reported conducting
51 Bible studies.
We thank them for showing us
another encouraging example
世界中の神の民を一致させる—
兄弟愛に関する 励みある模範を
示してくださっていることに感謝します
of the brotherly love that unites
God’s people worldwide.
兄弟たちが クリスチャン愛と
あいさつを送っています
They send us their Christian love
and greetings,
and we send our love in return,
along with prayers for Jehovah’s favor.
わたしたちもエホバの恵みがあることを
祈りつつ あいさつを送ります
We thank you for joining us,
プログラムをご覧くださったことに
感謝します
and we look forward
to an encouraging program next month.
来月のプログラムも楽しみにしましょう
ニューヨーク市ブルックリンから
JW Broadcastingでした!
From Brooklyn, New York,
this is JW Broadcasting!